Very, very happy to introduce our
next keynote speaker, Max Welling.
And he's one of the people
who really needs no introduction. So I'll
keep it very brief. But I can share
that as many of you probably know, Max
is a professor at University of Amsterdam and actually
is now running a startup called Cusp AI which I think
he'll be talking about today. And I'm
excited to hear his talk because Max has actually
had a very long history in the Eichler
community. You know, one of our first test of
time awards was given to auto
encoding variational base, which was an early
ICARE paper I think really
helped establish iCLEAR as a
front a a really one of the major conferences
in machine learning and since then
Max has done a lot of incredible work
on graph neural networks,
in addition to a lot of work on AI for science which
is what he'll be talking about today. So
leave it at that and let's welcome Max up the stage.
Can I have the slides? Yes. Great.
It's super nice to be here.
You for the kind introduction.
And, yeah. The talk is gonna be about
from physics to AI to materials
a journey from foundations to impact.
And indeed, it is true that I've been here
before as I'll say in a minute. To talk
the menu for today is
I'll, have first a word on science,
then I'll talk a bit about from physics to AI
making waves, then I'll talk a
bit from physics to AI and thermodynamics
of AI, then I'll
talk about from AI to materials, which is a start
up, and then I'll have an app
and epilogue. So he goes
to prologue.
First it is indeed true
that I was giving a keynote at the first
ever iCLEAR in 2013.
This was when you know
the size of the group was you know, you would
know everyone in in the in the room. It was a
small room with maybe 50 to a 100
people. And you
all here are definitely a testament
to how this field has
completely exploded.
So as the field has
exploded, also has
the way we are doing science. And it's
good to think about this for a moment.
In the old days, like way back,
you had researchers write each other letters.
Right? They thought about something long and hard and then
they wrote a letter and then they physically mailed it
to their to their colleague, and it took
weeks before a response came back.
So so science was slow.
It did it did actually result in
paradigm shifts. Like general
relativity. Modern research
is fast. It means
it's incremental, usually
and it is highly coupled. Every one of you is
highly to the rest. Everybody wants to work
on LLMs. Right?
Okay. So but the side effect of
that is that principle strange
new ideas are suppressed in this
environment. Basically, because
you cannot produce the bold numbers. Everybody's chasing
bold numbers, If it's hard to produce
bold numbers in your first paper, it is a
bit hard to get published. And I think this
is bad. We need to think about that.
So I propose that we really need to go to boldly
go where no one has won gone before,
Not everyone has to do that. But those who
do think should be rewarded and
not have reviewer two write a very
bad review.
And so where has this taken us? Right? The bitter
lesson really is the
lesson that we should scale. And it's nice
and predictable if you throw x amount more
compute at it, your model
will y become better. Right?
So it's predictable. Companies like it a lot.
And so, I call this scale your way out.
We're now talking about building
data centers into space.
The other side is innovate your way out.
Think hard about the problem. Shift the paradigm,
and here we have a researcher
researching the brain. And
figuring out that the brain actually uses 20
watt in order to
operate at about the same level of intelligence
as what we currently have. Which is
about a million to a billion. Times more efficient
than current hardware. So that I
would think if we figure out how the brain work, why
would we shoot data centers into space if
there is something in here
which would actually do the job for
us. And
this actually I presented this curve. I think it
was the first of its kind actually in 2018.
It's a log
linear curve. About the increase of
energy consumption or the increase of parameters
in your models, over time,
you can nicely see the bend
here when GPUs were invented, and
so we got on a faster exponential
acceleration. I predicted
then that in 2025, we would reach
a 100,000,000,000,000 parameter models, which
is about the number of synapses in our brain.
Actually don't know if we have reached that
number. This may be into trillions,
but maybe one or two orders of magnitude
off still. But we
are closing in on AGI for short.
And so that was the, introduction and I'll
now go to, Physics part one.
This is making waves. I'll
start first with celebrating ten years of symmetries
in AI. My student,
Takao Cohen, even at his when he did
his master's thesis and
after after his his PhD he wrote this paper in
2016 group equivariant
convolutional neural networks. And if
you want to learn about this,
now there is this book by written by Maurice Wyler
who was also in my group which is
a really nice introduction
in the field of if equivariance
lots of nice illustrations
and getting more and more mathy
towards the end.
And so to remind you, what is
equivarius again, it is
and you can read it here in this book and in fact
you know, these illustrations are from this book.
So if you start with an input image, which is
kind of a gecko on the plane, and
you know that a gecko doesn't really change
if you move the gecko from one place to the
other or you move the camera.
Then you want to hardwire that in your neural
net. And it's not given that your neural
network understands that. In fact, only convolutional
neural networks understand that.
So you what you want mathematically is
that if you filter the image, you get a filtered
image. And then
do the translation in your filtered space.
That should come out to be the same as
first translating the image and
then filtering. So this is a commutation
relation that you hold. If it holds, you're
in business, because now your neural
network is equivariant. And of course, it represents
a constraint on the parameters of your model.
An equivirance has made it into my
so the field that I really like, which is a r
for science. So
here's two ways in which, you know, my students
have worked on it. One of
them is building equivariance into graph
neural networks. And those can then be used
to learn force fields or machine
learning interatomic potentials
to be able to simulate
molecules. Much faster than if you would have
to do the quantum mechanical calculation.
They also made it into generative models, so
you can generate molecules from
noise. And those
also, have this equivariance
prior in them.
I'll now talk about a new
bold new proposal without bold
numbers, which is about
the wall of waves
in computation, in neural computation.
And this has been a journey for maybe
five to seven years or something like this. And
many people accompanied me on this journey.
It started with Andy Keller,
and, you know, and all these people here
have contributed to it. As
well. I I know Nabil
is here today. Who has contributed
to this particular,
project. So feel free to to
talk to him as well.
So in these days we build agents. Right?
And agents need to reason.
In order to reason, you need to hold things
in memory.
But how do we build systems that naturally
hold things in memory is the question.
And need to hold things in memory over long
spatial temporal time scales
or scales. Now the universe has solved
this problem. I will argue.
The way it solved it is by creating waves
or you know. Communicating with waves.
You look out to the stars, the reason you can even
see stars, because
electromagnetic waves hit your retina. Right?
In fact, even the brain turns
out to use waves and I'll go into
that a little bit more.
So first, I'll go do a little bit of history.
This is old work
mostly by This this is led
by Andy Keller. Where
we started to play around
with RNNs. We structured the
RNNs in such a way that they would naturally
create waves in their eternal
internal latent spaces. And so
we studied two tasks where you need memory
the copy task and the adding
task which make basically means you read something
at some time and then you have to hold it
in memory and regurgitate it at some time.
Could be a random time. Similar for the
adding time you have to sort of hold for
a number get another number, add them up, and then
add, you know, provide the sum. And if you look
at these latent representations, which are the
channels here, what you'll
find is that in the
sort of the one that creates waves, you
get like channels and it will
create an activation, and it will then hand it to
the next channel, and it will hand it to the next
hand it to the next channel, And so what happens is
this information spins around in these channels.
And the beauty is that that structure
really helped solve these
these problems where you need a long time memory.
Here's another work, we did with,
Takiro Miyato. He
worked on a neural network based
on so called Kuromoto oscillators.
These are models where you have
circles or complex numbers.
Every neuron has a direction, a phase as
well. They are coupled together
next to each other and they want to synchronize,
like actually, and this has is basis
in neuroscience because in neuroscience,
neurons binds together to create
representations for objects, and they do this
by synchronizing their waves.
Their oscillations. And so here you
can see how if you build a model
and you train it well, it will actually create these
nice traveling waves. Through these networks.
And then he did some tests and it worked surprisingly
well. I would say state of the art. Art.
And there was a few things that caught my eye
which were very interesting about this.
The first thing one the first one is if you
try to adversarially attack these now
these images, you'll find
that the smallest change you can
make to the input in order to change
the class of the of the input
actually created an image that looked
like the class you were trying to you know,
bring into. Which is very different
from the normal neural networks where you couldn't even
see the change in the input image
to get to get it to predict
a new class. And so, you know, if you
go from plane to bird, I can see a bird
If you could go from car to frog, you'll have
to squint a bit, but you see a frog.
Here's the head. Here's the here's the paw.
Shipped to horse. Frog to dog.
So to me this means that the input space is
smooth. If you take two inputs, and
you change them a little bit, what happens
is that, the
the prediction is smooth. Is it won't
change abruptly. He
also applied this to solving Sudoku
puzzles, which is clearly a reasoning task,
where you have to integrate information
over the entire image, and he found actually
that he could create state
of the art, on these Sudoku puzzles.
So I thought we were in the right direction.
And so more recently, I've been thinking about
is there a physics principle behind this?
Can we understand these kind of
more empirical intuitive ideas
better? And in order to illustrate this,
I brought a stick
and the stick is going to do a little experiment.
So if I put the stick here, the stick is beautifully
rotation invariant. Well, it's not quite rotational invariant. But
if you squint, you know, if you rotate it
like this, it doesn't change.
And now I'm gonna do an experiment.
I'm gonna break the symmetry So I can do
this by pushing here.
Okay. Like this. I can do this by pushing
here but that's clearly
is a, I am breaking the symmetry
because I decide to do this. Right?
There's another way to break the symmetry which is I'm gonna
push down remember if I push down it's
purely symmetric. Because you
know, if I rotate, it's still the same force. If I do this,
then you know, this happens. Right?
So the symmetry is still broken, but
now it's spontaneously broke. I
didn't do anything myself to break the symmetry.
But the natural stable state
has broken the symmetry. Alright.
My experiment.
Oh no. It's not actually. So there's two more things I wanna say
about this. So once you've done that,
you can get two kinds of oscillations. This is
the first oscillation. Right?
And I have to put energy in that oscillation.
That's called a Higgs mode. And yes,
that is the if you do this in quantum field theory,
you get Higgs particles, which create the mass
in the universe. That's pretty deep,
isn't it? The other one is, I can
do this. Now that doesn't
require me any energy. But
it's still a wave of a kind. And
that's called the Goldstone mode, these
are also modes, you know,
things in in physics. Okay.
So these are actually very the symmetry breaking is
very fundamental concept in
physics. If you take a liquid and a liquid if
you squint is definitely translation
invariant, And you
you lower the temperature at some
point that liquid will turn into a crystal.
Right? It's like water turns
into ice. And you've broken the symmetry
because the continuous symmetry, the
translation symmetry turn into a discrete
symmetry. Translation symmetry.
And that's a phase transition. So it's a very fundamental
concept in physics. And then
you have these goldstone modes. Right? Which are
these modes which I talked about. So
these modes are gold stone modes.
The equivalent of that Goldstone
mode, in fact, is what
we call phonons. In
crystals. So these are you
know, oscillations of all these atoms
that are moving, and they create travelling waves.
Also, we thought that should be a good candidate
for you know, trying to get those
things into our neural networks.
And the and the argument I want to make is that
they are useful because they can sort of act
memory. So here is a particular
evolution equation that physicists really like.
If you don't understand it's fine, it's it
creates waves. And there's a potential and
the potential, if you choose the potential to be this nice
Mexican hat, you have exactly the
situation that I described, The
symmetry that the system likes to sit in
this blue region and in order to get there
it needs to break the symmetry. And you have
these oscillations which go back and forth here, which
are the hex oscillations, and the ones that go around
which are the gold stone modes.
And then if you look at the at the waves that
you create, the waves you know,
of the ones that are you're flipping back
and forth here are like this.
And, what happens is that the different
frequencies start to mix. There is a dispersion
relation that involves kind of this
kind of mass term. And all the frequencies start
to mix together, and it's very hard to hold the information.
Where if you look at the one that that moves around
like this, you get these beautiful
waves that hold their shape
and move outward.
So here's that particular
movie made by Nabil. That
shows that very nicely these
the structure of the of the
of the wavefront is the same, which means you can store
information those wavefronts.
And Now I just mentioned that these things
are actually, discussed a lot in neuroscience.
And especially Terry Sanowski and Lyle
Miller which we whom we have been
working on this they're a big proponent
of actually understanding the
function of, of these waves in the brain.
And it's an interesting story because
the old days, people had only one electrode and you
could stick it somewhere in the brain course, you wouldn't
see any waves. But now they have
many multiple electrodes and many hundreds
of these electrodes they can put in. And now they can actually
see the waves that are going through the brain. So this
is a whole new developing field. And,
we wrote a paper together four
of us, on the relationship
between the neuroscience and the machine
learning and the symmetries. It's hopefully,
it's it's coming out soon in
nature perspective.
Okay. So how are we gonna build neural networks
that have this particular property? Right? So that
is not the the challenge.
And the way to do it is to go back to actually an
old idea maybe I think,
in the Jeff Hinton called this capsules.
Everything goes back to Jeff Hinton one way or the other.
So, you know, here's capsules. And
what we do is we create a neuron
and the neuron has an internal structure.
So it could be a doughnut,
or it could be a or an
end dimensional sphere with a little
vector in it. And the vector can move around. So
you can think of this as a spin in some sense.
And the equivariance in
these networks is if I start to spin around
these vectors in the in the input
layer, all the other
vectors in the internal and the output
will have to spin with the same phase.
And you can make these networks such that
they have this property. You have to you can't just bake it in.
And so the theory behind
it is this idea that we want to create
networks where information propagates
to many many hundreds or thousands
of layers of
either an RNN or a deep neural network.
And then you can study these networks as
a map, as an iterated map or
maybe even as dynamics.
And that we and there's this paper, by these
authors called deep information
they studied this. And they found that if the
networks live on the edge of chaos,
which I'll explain in a minute, they will perform
best. What does that mean? Well, there's a number of
phases. Like you know, phases in physics.
There's a phase where any two
inputs or any two inputs actually collapse
to the same point. This is a stable fixed point.
Or sort of an ordered phase, you'd call it.
There's another phase where any two
input, even if there are infinite testimony
close, they will eventually, and exponentially
fast, diverge they completely
decorrelate. And you can it becomes basically random.
You can best describe this as a as
a random iterate.
And that is you also lose information
about the input. Right? If it collapses or as
it becomes chaos, you all lose information
about the input. But it's something the
middle that you can fine tune to
which is called edge of chaos, where the
information propagates through the whole neural network.
And in fact, right before this, I
I Googled for you know,
if this actually I've heard that this actually
the brain is also on the edge of chaos, so you'll find
it very quickly. And it says the human
brain is on the edge of chaos. And since it's
by the University of Cambridge, it must be true. So that's
good.
Okay. So let's dig a little bit into
the mathematics of this. So what we are doing
is we create a neural net and we
randomly put weights on the
we draw random weights and we put them in the neural net.
Now because the activations are a function of
the weights, the activations also become
random. Right? Now
if we take the initial distribution
of the weights to be have small variance,
get through this thing where my my little
vector on my sphere will
collapse to a point. I don't want
that. But now if I take
it larger than certain threshold, it goes
through a phase transition. And you will
now get that your your sphere
gets mapped to a bigger sphere.
And we don't have to find you anything here. We just
have to get over this threshold. And that's very good.
The information can be encoded in the the the
various phases of these spins.
And they and the aquivaryance make sure that
I can propagate that information
all the way through my neural network. And the important
pieces that we don't have to fine tune And
you can see with a small experiment that
the theoretically know,
derived transition between these
two phases also is the is
where where neural networks starts to
work.
And then, so I'll I'll close
this particular section with some
preliminary results. I should say,
thank you to Andy, because I think he worked through the
night to produce these results.
And so Andy, wherever you are,
you are a hero. Now I can actually show these
particular results. Well he did
was he looked at the number of parameters in your
neural network. And then he trained both
RNNs and GRU. RNNs with
GRU functions. And then you had
versions of that which had this
internal structure, either a sphere with
k dimensions or k to
minus one dimensions, I guess, and and or
a u one symmetry.
And then he plotted the performance
on a task which is called permuted
mnist, where you make the task
harder by permuting the pixels. We
you have to keep things in memory.
You make it harder, you look at you
know, how well do they do as a
function of the number of parameters. And you find
that the symmetries really help you
train these models well with less parameters.
And to inspect a little bit,
how these internal channels
work. So here are the channels in in a normal RNN,
they turn on and then they stay on for a while,
and then they turn off. But then these
internal degrees, these internal spin degrees
of freedom, the magnitudes are somewhat stable.
But then if you look closely here,
you'll see 24 channels. And
they kind of oscillate. So this is a vector that moves
around in this space.
And here actually on this, you see
the trajectory of the two principal projected
onto the two principal components of some
of these neurons you'll
see that they they oscillate around. Right? So
there's now internal oscillations
that hold on to the information.
Okay. So that was the first part.
And now I'll move on to the second part. Which
is different but also not different.
But I'll reset a little bit and say
that, you know, yes, we are in a very special
time. Sort of the same time
as the people in the eighteenth century,
when the steam engine was invented, where where we're
let me say, enhance or augment you
know, human labor with machine
labor. You could also say replace, but
you know, it's it's subtle.
And now we are in a time when
we are enhancing or augmenting
human intelligence. With machine
intelligence. This is the AI revolution.
And it's interesting because we're in the middle
of it.
So we decided to write a book about it. In fact
you know, we just didn't get it out in time,
but you can pre order it. This is a bound
for but if you wanna have a look, this
is the book. And the book is written
together with, Siri Lou and Lars
Voldyke. Lars is somewhere here in the audience as
well. And this
tries to study the deep relationship
between a field and physics. We'll
stochastic thermodynamics, which is an extension
of normal thermodynamics, which deals with equilibrium,
situations. To non equilibrium
And of course, AI is all about
non equilibrium. And
we found that they share the same probabilistic,
math basically
And it is systems that describe
you know, systems that Sorry. It is a
theory that describes systems that lose information.
And then I asked Gemini to
visualize how you
know, this could be related to time
reversal symmetry breaking and I got a somewhat
dark image. I thought it was
appropriate because we some sometimes I think we
live in somewhat dark times.
But here on this side,
is the phase. If you look at the microscopic
physics, it's actually time reversal
symmetric. So if you look at a bunch of molecules
which are moving around, and
you reverse it, goes the other direction, but you
don't know if that's forward in time or backward in
time. On the other side,
the sign, the time reversal symmetry
is broken.
Which means that we have a direction of time. So
I am going to talk until the end
in one direction. Unfortunately, I cannot go back in
time and get myself a little bit more time for this
talk. And, it's
appropriate that things break. I think Gemini
took breaking a little too serious on this side.
But things do break, when
you have entropy. Things degrade.
And so it's a it's a theory about
how losing
in how to lose information and how to describe
that. Right? And a map that you cannot
run backwards is a map that loses information.
And, we probably, hopefully, all know
this equation, which is a Markov chain
which is the equation that actually
describes systems that lose information In
fact, if you run a market chain long enough, it's well
known you have completely forgotten your initial
state. And so you start with an initial
distribution. This is the path. Of the state
And then you have these transition probabilities and as
a control parameter lambda.
And then in physics, losing information basically
is equivalent to entropy production. So
every system that loses information produces
entropy of some kind.
And there is a beautiful theorem which I don't think
many people know here, which is called Crook's
fluctuation theorem. That that quantifies
very precisely what that means.
So it says, if I have this forward
distribution, over a path,
and then I look at the backward distribution.
So this is the same dynamics with the same
diffusion. But I start at the end
and I apply the control signal
in reverse. In the other direction. If it
were reversible, I would end up with exactly the
same state. If it weren't reversible,
I end up in some other state. And
the ratio between these two
probability distributions over paths
is e to the total entropy production of
the system. No.
And I'll tell you a little bit basic
thermodynamics. If you don't like equations, you can stare
at this equation. This this figure from,
Gemini and try to work out what what
I'm trying to say in a figure. But let me
go through the equations. So I
have a state, which is a, you
know, an arbitrary state from zero
to to the final time t. And
the first law of thermodynamics says that the total
energy of the system or the
sort of total change in the energy of a system,
must be equal to the total work done
on the system plus the total heat
that's flowing into the system. These
two terms determine
the amount of energy that's changing.
There's another really fundamental equation
which is the train the change in free energy.
That says, that the change in free energy
is the change in energy minus
the temperature times the change in the entropy.
And I will come back to this equation, but it basically
says that this is
the energy that's free to do work.
And it's not all the energy because
all the degrees of freedom you've lost
information about you can actually not
do very effective work with.
Okay. And now we get to this very fundamental equation,
which says that what is the actual work
you're doing on a system that's out of equilibrium?
It's given by we can
sort of use these two equations, is
given by the total work done minus
the change in the free energy. This by you get
this by combining these two.
Sorry. No. That's the definition of dissipated work.
And by using these equations, you can e relate
this to t times a change of
the entropy of the system, minus the heat
that you're generating.
And that the definition of this is actually
t t times the total entropy production.
But now what's interesting is some
very recent results actually show
that that is
lower bounded by
the Wasserstein distance, the two
the squared, two Wasserstein distance
squared, between the initial
distribution and the final distribution,
divided by the time you take to get there. So
the faster you wanna move something,
the more work you will have to do.
And so that actually
proves I think or that has
this very strong argument that,
this is a limit to superintelligence. Right? Because
if I have a thought I need to
change the distribution of my internal
neurons, my latent representations. I need to
change it, otherwise I don't have a thought.
In order to change it, have to satisfy
this equation because one distribution has to go to the other
distribution, If I want to
think fast, I'm gonna pay more have to
use more energy. If I want to if I can do
it slow, I have a, you know, I can
get close to zero. But who wants to think slow?
Okay. So then, I do this little derivation,
which is we start from the Crooks' equality.
And the Crookes' equality, you can just move this
there and you move this guy here then.
And then you integrate over paths, And
what you'll get is this equation. Which
is that if I take a
path I start at the big initial state.
I sample a point and I sample to my
final state under a controlled
sequence. Right? And I do
this many times. And then I
average e to the minus the work done
over each one of these paths. Then
in fact, I can equate that to e to
the minus change in free energy.
So here is a way to
estimate the free energy, which is actually very difficult to
do. And it's called the Gerzynski
equality. And even when Radford
Neill wrote his paper on annealed importance sampling,
in that paper, he says that
this is equivalent to the JERZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZYZ So
isn't that beautiful? That actually
these two things got independently
kind of sort of discovered.
And and, you know, from these two different fields. To
me, it's a testament that we're actually
looking at the same problem.
And entropy is a truly deep concept and
so I wanna dive a little bit deeper into this
with you. And
people actually when, you know, thermodynamics
was invented really didn't understand
this this this entropy.
And actually Boltzmann, I think
went almost mad he wasn't
understood that he had, you know, his interpretation.
And so the the thought experiment is I have
a little demon and the demon
actually has access to all the information
about the individual atoms
in the box. There's blue
atoms which are slow and
the demon knows where the atom is and
at what speed it's moving. And where it's going.
And then there is also
hot ones. And it has
a little door and it you turn out it turns out you can
open and close the door without doing any work.
And he opens the door whenever a fast particle
comes in and he keeps the door closed when it's a
slow particle. And in doing that, he
will separate the
slow the cold atoms from the hot atoms.
But now it can do work. Because now it
can close the door and then the hot
and then let the door move as
a slider and the door will move to
one side. And that will create work.
So in principle, this daemon can build
a Perpetual Mobili.
As long as he has access to
the information. Of course, the problem is he will
not have access to the information. He will lose the information.
And that's exactly the entropy
the physical system. And from this we conclude
that Shannon entropy
and physical entropy, bosom entropy are truly
the same thing. And I think that's
pretty deep. In fact, you can go one step further
which is it's subjective. Because
one demon knows more about the system than
another demon knows about system. And
therefore, the entropy for one demon will
be different for the other demon. So
actually, entropy is Bayesian. A
way.
And so there is this know,
interesting analogy. I'll just start on this
side because most people will know this
side. It is maybe
before the deep learning area, some era, so
maybe most people forgot it. But,
you can write down let's say z
are degrees of freedom that
we have lost track of. We don't know
where they what they precisely are. We just have a distribution
over them. And x are the data.
These are the observations. And
then we all know that the posterior distribution is
given by basic. Rule.
Which is this is Bayes rule.
And then Hinton and, Mead,
Rutherford Neill Hinton and the Reverend Neal, they
wrote down the variation of free energy, which
is the same thing we used for the variation
of outer encoder, or also known as the ELBO,
evidence lower bound. And
it's defined as minus log probability
over the observed data.
And you can upper bound it by the variational
free energy by introducing a variational
q. And look at and and define
that's defined as the x
And minus the entropy of
q. And on the
other side, we have the Boltzmann
distribution, which is the equilibrium distribution
of a of a physical system. Which
has HSD
as the energy function.
And then on physics, of course, we also have a
we have free energy of a system at equilibrium
which is given by minus the log of the partition
function. And for non equilibrium systems,
you can upper bound it by this free energy
which is the expectation of the energy under
the system out of equilibrium,
minus the entropy. Of that system. And if you
compare these two you'll you'll see
they're basically the same. And
on this side, when we do when
we minimize the free energy, we we
minimize it over q, which is the e step
in the e m algorithm.
And the m step which is minimize f
over p, which is learning. It's a
learning step. On the other
side, you would relax f
over q, which is you relax the
physical system, You would generate entropy
and heat. And if you change
h, which will be learning, you actually
perform work on the system.
And actually in this book we, you know,
sort through many
you know, relationships between these two fields.
You know, when we do inference or learning or
control, or transport,
in, you know, in machine learning,
like, you know, with these particular tools like diffusion
models or
and Bridge Optum Control or MCMC variation
of free energy, These things actually
have an equivalent in
this theory of stochastic thermodynamics. That's why
I think it's worth to read about it because there's
a lot of things the physicists did which we can use.
There's actually kind of a nice you
know, sort of dictionary you can you
can come up with and I I will highlight
this one stochastic normalizing flows
is equal to escorted free energies
estimation in physics,
and optimal transport continuous normalizing
flows is called counter diabetic
driving in physics.
Okay. And of course, we all
know that you know, diffusion models
are at the heart of this
bridge. In fact, the original paper,
if you can read it I can't.
Said, deep unsupervised learning
using non equilibrium thermodynamics. Right? This
is a paper by Yasha Sol Dixin at all.
So they made the connection.
And so what happens is you have a system that
follows the laws of physics. In particular, it
follows the second law of thermodynamics.
You start with structure,
and you let it age like
we all age. Right? And then in the end,
it turns into noise. Like we
turn into dust at one day, unfortunately.
And then you study that process and you try
to invert it. You say, okay, every
little step let me create a
force and do some work to move
in the other direction. Right? So this one goes
against the second law of thermodynamics,
It is like an egg that you
you turn into an omelette, This is
like the omelette that turns into an egg. You don't
actually see this happen in the real world,
but you know, you could engineer it to happen if you're
smart enough.
And so we set out to use this
theory to actually
for something useful which is compute
the free energy difference
between let's say, a drug like molecule
that is unbounds to a protein
and a drug like molecule which is bound to
a protein. You need that
because you wanna figure out how
how well does that molecule
like to sit in a particular pocket
of the protein. But it's actually
very difficult calculation to do. And
so what you need to do, if you just do MD simulation
and you wait, you will wait forever.
So you need to control it. So you need to apply a
force to drive it into the
pocket. And then later
compensate for it. But now
we know how to do that. We can
train a diffusion model because or or a flow
model. Which basically takes the
initial distribution, and we know then
how to find forces or
velocities or whatever we call them to
move that, to flow that into another distribution.
So we train that model, and then we can use
the Jarsinski equality, which I just
explained in quite a bit of detail to measure
over every step how much work did we do
and then compute this expectation over the e
to the minus work and that will give
you an estimate for the free energy. And now
you think this is great, this will work fantastic,
until you try and then you figure out this
is actually a very high variance estimator.
Because it's in the exponent
and it's basically the large
the paths which have a lot a
large amount of work completely dominate
that estimate. So you need to do something about
it. Now it turns out
is a generalized Jazinsky quality, and
this is cool because this is something we
can directly import from this physics
theory. The generalized equality
says, if you have a control force you
can, you know, I won't go into the details.
If you optimize for certain
paths, which are much less noisy, you
can get rid of that noise. And
in fact, it's an optimal transport solution.
So you need to solve the optimal transport problem
between the initial distribution and the
final distribution and those paths
that that kind of control path you take
is the optimal one. And it has zero
variance if you do it right. That's amazing.
Zero variance.
And so we know how to do this. There's a paper
called you know, optimal
transport continuous normalizing flows by these guys
here, Tom at all, where, you know, this
would be the normal diffusion model and this
would be the optimal transport
diffusion model. Right? The straight lines
you you match the you match the
the particles you match the the
samples and then you have a straight line between
them.
And this is the paper we wrote about this. So if you
wanna learn, it's actually here at iCLEAR.
So you can you can check it out in one of the poster sessions.
Or talk to Lars, which is somewhere here.
Okay. So then, the last part of this talk
I wanna talk about
from foundation to impact. So I've been working
on foundations my whole life,
and in the last stretch. Of
that, career, I wanted to do something
useful finally.
And so I cofounded this company
called Cost AI. And
what does it do? It will
help design materials using
AI. And let me try
to relate that back to thermodynamics.
So
let's say I am in the business
of designing you know, drugs or something.
I come up with my first design.
And I In order to evaluate that particular
drug, I will have to go through
lots of simulations which will cost me a lot
of energy and therefore money.
And, and then I figure out actually it wasn't actually
a very good drug after all. So I come up
with my next design.
Now I could go through the same sequence of things
again, but the
devil in me or the demon in me
actually thinks well maybe I should store
the information from the first. Rung.
In a big database. And then
the information from the database
we can use that to train neural networks.
That is moving the information from the
database into the
weights of a neural network. And then next
time around, what I can do is
use the information
from my neural network to either directly predict
the properties, which is very very cheap,
or use train maybe a machine learning inter atomic
potential or force neural
network force to
accelerate this particular MD simulation.
Okay. So that's cool because now
I have used, I've kind of amortized the
amount of effort I made
I've learned from my first
simulations and I've used that to accelerate
the next ones, which means I am using less energy.
For the next round. So that is
literally Maxwell's demon
situation. So we
built this platform
and the platform can be most easily thought
about as a
search engine. Although this one searches
not over existing molecules like
you know, a search engine searches
over existing
you know, I would say
documents or images. Actually, I would say maybe
modern search engines also create
text and create images, or maybe it's better
compared to that. And
so start with a with a prompt.
Say, I want a material and it needs to have these properties
and, you know, it cannot be toxic and,
you know, all these kinds of things. Right? And so
that goes to the agent. So at the at the heart of this
is a is a COSPA agent that is orchestrating
a big computation and the first
thing it does is say, okay, does that mat Is there actually
material that satisfies these properties?
We have we have big databases from
the various
you know, publishing houses, that will help
us look for materials that
have the right properties. And you know, let's say that was
disappointing, so then we go to our generative models.
So now we're going to generate
molecules candidate molecules,
which have the right properties.
And of course, when we generate them, we have to
also evaluate them. So we have this multiscale
stack of, you know, of let's say, digital
twin stack of of evaluating
all of these molecules.
And then after all that has sort of
converged, we go to experimental layer
hopefully, this is a self driving lab of kind
so we get lots of feedback about data.
And when that is done, we go
actually expose the results
to to the to the chemist
the chemist thinks, it's actually not what he wanted,
and they they refine
the prompt. Right?
So that's how that works. And now I'm gonna
actually announce something which I'm very
very excited about and this is
able hopefully go live now
or right after, I don't know.
This is a new
framework for molecular
dynamic simulations that we developed
at COSP and that we are open sourcing to the world.
This was done by Jonas Koller and Nicholas
Gao. Those are the the heroes
of this story. They put a huge amount of work
of creating that. Collaboration with
NVIDIA. And it is a JAX
based toolkit for
atomistic simulations.
And it's a Python and GPU
native. So it will actually
operate very fast on GPUs.
What is very interesting about that is you can
just take your force field, your
machine learning force field, and compile
it into JAX and then run it directly
into this MD simulation.
It's built around batching so you can do many computations
at the same time on, you know, maximally using
your GPUs. And it runs
natively on accelerators. One of them GPUs,
but also GPUs and all.
And you know, we of course we benchmarked it
and we get quite nice
sort of higher throughput on
both MD and
what you call canonical Monte Carlo
which which we need. I'll just I'll just illustrate
this. Okay. So first maybe
maybe a few more words about this. So it
has different ensembles both in MCMC
and MD. Simulations. It can also do
geometry optimization. We have
Colomb, interactions using a wall
simulations in them. We have Leonard Jones
and all sorts of some more classical
forces in them. But maybe the most exciting thing is
you can just take your favorite machine
learning force field compile
it, to JAX and run it
in the MD simulator. Okay.
So here's an example. This is actually one of
the first projects we did at COSP which is
trying to come up with a metal organic framework
that would be very good at capturing
carbon dioxide from the atmosphere
and, and regenerating afterwards. And what
you need to do then is you need to compute
these isotherms, which is at different
pressure levels and different temperatures
you need to figure out how much c o two sticks
to the inside of the pores
of this metal organic framework.
And so here's the simulator that would run.
So you throw in ran at random
positions, you throw in these carbon
dioxide molecules. And you let them wiggle around
until they kind of bind to something
and then at the end, you figure out how much got stuck
there. Here's another
example. This is basically a batch relaxation
of a meta organic framework. Run with
the Ooma, force field.
Which we just compiled, from PyTorch
into into JAX.
And, you know, the nice thing here is, of course,
you can run a large batch of
these minimizations all parallel.
And this one is also very exciting
I think. So this is a particular
sort of diffusion process that we studied
called hopping of
protons in sulfuric sulfuric
acid. And so this is kind of
illustrated here. You have water molecules
and they and they move these
protons, these hydrogen atoms,
between, you know, those water molecules.
So they they hop water
molecules creating h three o plus in the
middle. And so, so these these
little green dots are sulfuric acid.
The red, sort of flashes
are these you know, when
we actually observe in simulation these these
these jumps. And then
these are, you know, these blue things are the
HR three plus.
Sort of places where the hop happened.
And we can show that we can actually very
clearly reproduce the radial distribution functions
even better than some of the DFT calculations,
which is, this
one. The the PBE
one. Okay.
That was the announcement yeah, I'll
show the QR codes in a in a
minute and you can download the code
and and play around. And let me know how you like it.
So undeniably,
the AI for science revolution is here.
I am very excited about this. We are seeing massive
progress.
On the you know,
and materials
innovation, and climate modelling
and many more fields.
And I'm gonna highlight this
year because, both of these students are here and they
are very very smart. You should check them out.
One is for Eichelbelum and the other one is Marcin Zizh.
None of And
what happens here is, this is
variational flow matching This is
a version of flow matching
based on probability distributions where you actually
estimate the probability distribution and,
use it also to predict in
a in one step basically to generate,
molecules. And the other one is a
sort of a new transformer, which
is very fast
in order to model weather and
storms. And that paper
is actually out here
and you can, find Maxim to to talk
about it. So
then in conclusion, on
a slightly more serious note, but I think it kinda
resonates with the the talk of
this morning. And I didn't put it in afterwards.
This was already in my talk.
We are living in technologically disruptive
time. And this is very exciting to be in that particular
disruptive time.
But we are, I mean, this room, all
of you plus maybe
two or three more of these rooms, We
are developing this technology. Right?
We are very special in that sense.
And in a way, we are all Oppenheimer's. That's
the way I view it. Because we are building
a powerful technology that has potential
dual use. Now, it has dual use. It
can be used for good and for bad like any
other powerful technology. And
I feel this comes with great responsibility.
I'm not gonna tell you what to work on and what not to
work on and who to work with, etcetera.
But I do ask you, to make
conscious choices about what to work on. Think
about. What you want to work on and
do not look away from the problem.
And so this is the final slide for me.
So if you wanna check out these two
QR codes, you'll find the code and the blog
for for cups, which is the
the MD simulator. And I'll leave it at that. Thank
you very much.
I guess you're already there. So
Thanks so much for the great talk.
So could you comment on the importance of
reliability in in a scientific,
in science in general? So
trustworthy discovery and so on. And
specifically, perhaps for casp
does your agent, suffer
from hallucinations? And is that,
like, a problem, in practice or not?
Really? Yeah. That's a good question.
Typically, yeah, it can
it can it's it's doing an optimization
this optimization could be
it could do way too many expensive
calculations, let's say. And so you
have to put in some guardrails that if the
costs start to grow, you wanna check
things. And you consider
measure how well it's doing relative to standard methods
like Bayesian optimization.
In general if you have agents to
have uncertainty in them. And
in fact, one of our recent papers with Dario
Crocha
has exactly is a transformer
actually a LoRa based
transformer. That adds
uncertainty to the predictions.
And, that could be very useful in this particular
case.
So I don't know precisely who goes when.
Is do you wanna point to something? Okay.
I guess, I don't know. You have to look
at each other who was first and then play
Hi. Thank you Max.
Quantum field theory is such a rich field.
Are there any other
methods that would be applicable
to AI research from quantum field
day? For example, like the randomization group
or some other types of techniques.
Know, in your Yeah. The answer is definitely yes, but the renormalization
group theory thing is already done. There
is a paper we've written called
God g u d,
which is basically,
mapping renormalization
group theory to sort of
diffusion models. So that
one you can just look up. But, yeah,
I think I think it's that's
what also this book is about. It
is there is a lot of really smart stuff
in these physics fields.
And if you have a physics background,
if you can find the bridge between them
you can you can walk the bridge in two directions.
Right? So it's like smart ideas can
make it into AI
but AI can also really help
you know, push the the, you know, the frontier
of these physics fields forward. So I think
that's why I love a f for science so much. Thank you.
You. Thank
you. Hello. Thank you Max for
this inspiring talk. I have a question
that has haunted me for quite a long
time. I'm glad that you talked about
the connection between
Shana entropy and the thermodynamic
entropy.
My question is that, we know
this this Landauer's law
specifying that you raise it one bit, it
would, cost the KBT times
l m two. This bit this bit
of a energy, right? Are you able
to predict how much
energy the cost to to
train something to
to to deal with the amnesty data or image
set data set. Yeah. It can
predict the the theoretical minimum
And and how far away the
brain away from that? How far away is the
GPU or GPU away from that?
Yeah. These are great questions actually. So
and there is a whole field actually
I I went to a conference in Japan on
this topic and there's a whole field of physicists
that actually thinks very deeply about the relationship
between computation and thermodynamics. Stochastic
thermodynamics. So people study actually
precisely this problem. So what is
the minimal amount of compute I would need
to invest in order to reach a certain result?
And I can't I can't give you the answer
to how far the brain is away from it.
But, yeah. So these these are great questions
that need to be researched and I think we'll
we'll discover lots of really interesting things
when we study these questions. Okay.
But it's great to know that there are actually people
trying to ask this questions. Yes. There is a whole field.
I can I can point you to it? Jostinski
and Crooks are in the community.
But there's a whole bunch of other people as well.
Yeah. Okay. Yeah. Thank you, Val.
Hi. Loved your work.
I just wanted to ask,
with your company and all,
how are you facing the problem of
synthetic accessibility and making sure those
molecules that you Yeah. Predict actually
go to a are synthesizable and
Yes. Making a blank. Two ways.
The first one is we look up
in our databases if things have been synthesized
which are very similar. So, we have a similarity
metric that extracts all the
all the molecules which are similar and then look
at their synthesis recipes
That's the first approach. The second
approach is we compute things like
free energy Use the free energy computation. If you can
estimate the free energy, of the
molecule, that you are, producing
and you find that other versions of this
have higher free energy, then that will
form most likely. So there is there is
these kind of computational as well as kind of I would
say literature approaches or
or or matching things to
literature or recipes that have already
been published.
Hello. I loved your talk.
I just wonder, back in the
day when we used to do umbrella sampling
or blue moon sampling,
for the free energy Yeah. Calculations out
of equilibrium, I mean, although you
could achieve the sample in the problem was most of
the time the reaction coordinates.
So I was reading your job. Whether
you is that part of
the learning? To select the reaction
coordinates in order to perform the out of equilibrium
calculation or just took
it at home? So you could argue that the nice thing
about this method is that you don't need a reaction
coordinates. Because the thing about a reaction coordinates,
you have to choose one before
you start. And that
already influences the success you will
have. And so these
these ones don't do not require you to to
you you can after you've trained your diffusion
model, you could potentially try
to extract a reaction coordinate
and then maybe use umbrella sampling
on that reaction coordinate. We haven't tried
that. We have we have
compared to, FEP
free energy perturbation methods.
Also with neural nets and know, they they were
they are pretty close. The ones that I showed in
FEP best ones are pretty close, I would
say.
Hello. Thank you for the talk.
You mentioned about algorithms
for generating molecules that satisfy
the certain properties. Yep.
My, first question is that
how much those properties are
close to real life drug
discovery scenarios, Uh-huh. And my second
question is that in your opinion,
the current evaluation metrics
or benchmark, how much they
are, close to the algorithms
that recently were developed,
to generate such molecules. Yeah.
Think what you're aiming at, which is a very good
question, which is that
the things you do in a computer
do not actually reflect real life.
And so you have to go then through the experiment
as well and and then actually extract lots of information
from the experiment But even then you're
not there. Because then you have to
even go to putting this material
in a process or creating it at
scale or in a reactor or something like this.
And then again, everything will change a bit.
So your ability
to model these systems
like the the actual
like system, the the actual material
operating in a real situation. A
real process, that is really key, but
it is also very hard. Problem.
So it's not you could argue
also depends a lot on the on the application area. I
think for semiconductors, we are pretty
good in being able to
simulate that For other things like
a telesys, there's probably a quite
big gap.
Sure we could keep Max here all day asking him
questions, but think, give him
a break and to give you know, to to move on to
the break, let's have one more question if if you don't mind.
Okay. Thanks for your presentation. I have a
single simple question. Don't
you think that,
rapid AI driven growth
of life sciences, especially
maybe biology, is not actually bound by
developing AI, but rather
by collecting more data. Yeah. Yeah. Good
point. I think
I would say it's the combination of the two.
So but definitely the
data is the key component.
Otherwise, you cannot train any models.
But in order to analyze
these huge amounts of data or
make use of it, you really need the AI. So
I think it's a combination of the two
One without the other, you're not gonna make a lot of
progress. Thank you. Thank you.